Well, by conservative reckoning in the
1960s, it was high time to bag up the
stupid liberalism of the New Deal and
Great Society era, put it by the curb,
and let a guy in a jumpsuit take it to
the dump where it will be at last
returned from the stinky chasm from
whence it came. So, it's time to talk
about it, and if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay, so hopefully I've established in
the last few videos that the
multitudinous policies that made up the
Great Society represented the golden age
of modern American liberalism. Like, you
couldn't go anywhere in the 1960s
without bumping into a liberal policy.
And then in addition to that, the 1960s
was a decade of enormous cultural
upheaval that included the Civil Rights
Movement and the discarding of social
norms that came with the youth
counterculture movement, to name only a
few developments. And as it happened,
the very rapidity of those changes
unsettled many conservative Americans
who seemed to perceive all the change
not as progress, but as an existential
threat. And therefore, in the 1960s, a
new conservatism began to stir, and its
members desired to take back what they
believed had been taken from them in the
throes of Civil Rights and liberalism.
And that take back essentially had three
prongs of attack. First, new
conservatives wanted to prevent what
they perceived to be moral and cultural
decline. For example, conservatives were
deeply dismayed by the discarding of
sexual norms that they witnessed in the
counterculture movement, and they feared
that the emphasis on casual free love
would unravel the most fundamental
institution of American culture, the
family. And then related to that, the
growing feminist movement challenged the
conservative narrative that society
thrives best when men and women embrace
their natural gender roles. And here
were all these saucy women getting
abortions and throwing their bras into
trash cans and letting their armpit hair
grow out, and worst of all, demanding
social equality with men. Or to put it
another way, these conservatives felt
like the Civil Rights Movements and the
anti-war movements amounted to little
more than social chaos, and they aimed
to bring back a sense of normalcy to
Americans. And then second,
conservatives sought to limit the role
of the federal government in American
society. And look, they weren't just
making this up. Recall that the New Deal
greatly expanded the power of the
federal government, and that liberal
tide just kept rising with the flurry of
federal civil rights policies, and
culminated in LBJ's Great Society. And
whereas liberals interpreted this
stretch of 30 years as long overdue
progress toward a more just and
equitable society, conservatives
interpreted it as a profound violation
of the United States federalist
structure since power had gradually
shifted away from the states and toward
the national government. Therefore, a
hallmark of the new conservatism would
be a strong emphasis on states' rights.
And then the third emphasis of this
conservative movement was to enact a
more aggressive foreign policy. And if
you've been paying attention throughout
this whole unit, you might be like,
"Uh, what?" And your confusion would be
justified because the Korean War, the
Vietnam War, and all the other proxy
wars that were launched in the name of
containing the spread of communism
really makes it seem like Americans
didn't really have problems with acting
aggressively in their foreign policy.
But even so, some of these new
conservatives believed that the United
States needed to make full use of its
power on the world stage. For example,
they attacked the gradual escalation
strategy of the Vietnam War enacted
mostly under a string of liberal
presidents, which ultimately ended in
national disgrace. And therefore, new
conservatives believed that American
foreign policy ought to be far more
assertive and aggressive. Okay, so those
are the big ideas that animated
conservatives in this period. But here's
where I tell you that at the beginning
of the 1960s, new conservatives were a
somewhat isolated and disjointed bunch.
But at least three developments brought
them together and helped give form to
their movement to give American
liberalism a proper smack bottom. First
was the publication and growth of a
conservative magazine called the
National Review. It first emerged in
1955 as the brainchild of conservative
activist William F. Buckley, and as it
grew in popularity, the publication
served to unify the various strands of
conservative thought, namely the
cultural traditionist, the free market
libertarians, and anti-communists. And
as such, Buckley helped provide the new
conservative movement with a consistent
ideological foundation to fight against
what they perceived as the morally
corrosive and economically destructive
effects of liberalism. And then the
second development that focused the new
conservatism was the campaign of Barry
Goldwater. So in the 1964 election,
Goldwater ran against Lyndon B. Johnson,
and in doing so, became the face of this
new conservative movement. And in this
campaign, Goldwater attacked New Deal
liberalism and advocated for the
abolition of Social Security benefits
and the progressive income tax and other
policies that he believed represented
federal overreach. And in these attacks,
Goldwater clearly articulated what would
become a staple of conservative politics
from then on, namely an emphasis on
states' rights against the intrusion of
the federal government. For example, by
that reasoning, Goldwater condemned the
Brown v. Board of Education ruling as
well as the Civil Rights Act of 1964
because they represented an
unconstitutional infringement of the
rights of states to enact policies that
suited their own constituency. However,
as would be the case with many
conservatives that followed in
Goldwater's steps, his emphasis on the
reduction of federal spending was mainly
limited to liberal safety net programs
like food stamps or social security. But
when it came to federal spending on the
military, Goldwater was all for it.
Anyway, ultimately, Goldwater lost in a
landslide to Johnson, but in the next
election, conservatives would finally
have their moment. And that leads us to
the third big development in this rise
of new conservatism, namely the election
of Richard Nixon to the presidency. So,
Nixon was a conservative who won the
election of 1968 and in doing so,
brought many of the principles of the
new conservatism onto the national
stage. For example, Nixon declared
himself the law and order candidate,
which actually was a thinly veiled code
for cracking down on minority crime in
urban areas. He also pledged to restrain
the federal government from regulating
and enforcing civil rights legislation,
not least the laws mandating integration
through school busing programs. And all
this taken together made up what became
known as Nixon's Southern Strategy,
through which he appealed to white
Southern voters who had reliably voted
Democrat. Like Nixon wasn't dumb enough
to come right out and say that racial
inequality and segregation was, now that
he thought about it, a pretty good idea.
But by using the coded language of
states' rights and law and order, he was
able to appeal to Southern voters who
had become deeply unsettled by the rapid
pace of social change over the previous
decade or two. And so, Nixon claimed
that there was a large and disgruntled
silent majority of Americans who were
fed up with all the cultural upheaval
and would show themselves in great
numbers to vote for a candidate that
promised to calm the waters and make
life more comfortable for the white
middle class. And as it turned out, he
was right because he won that election
handily. And in his first term, he got
busy dismantling many Great Society
programs and stacking the Supreme Court
with conservative judges. Okay, so as
conservatives gained more political
power in the 1970s, they continued to
clash with liberals on a metric buttload
of issues, only two of which I'm going
to tell you about. First of all,
liberals and conservatives clashed over
the issue of women's rights. So, on the
left, second-wave feminists called for
greater and greater social equality with
men, and that amounted to a threat to
conservatives for two reasons. First,
the 1973 Supreme Court decision in Roe
v. Wade legalized a woman's right to
abortion in all 50 states. And women's
rights activists cheered this decision
as a significant step in recognizing a
woman's right to make decisions
regarding her own body. But,
conservatives grew uncomfortable with
the women's liberation movement and
sought to limit access to abortion by
emphasizing that what a woman carried in
her womb was not merely a collection of
cells, but rather a human being that
possessed, even in that fetal state, the
right to exist. And then second, women's
rights activists pushed for an Equal
Rights Amendment that would formally
enshrine women's equality into the
Constitution. And while women's rights
activists were able to muster
significant support for this amendment,
conservative women like Phyllis Schlafly
organized a mass movement to kill the
amendment, and it ultimately fell two
votes short of ratification. And then
the second prominent clash between
liberals and conservatives was a
disagreement concerning the appropriate
amount of power for the federal
government. So, liberals of the New Deal
and Great Society varieties wanted more
involvement from the federal government
in order to expand access to civil
liberties and intervene in the economy
to avoid a crisis. But, conservatives
reacted strongly to both of these
points. So, as champions of states'
rights, the New Right of the 1970s
argued that the civil rights policies of
the Great Society era amounted to
federal coercion. And to support this
argument, they invoked the 10th
Amendment, which says that any power not
explicitly granted to the federal
government is reserved for the states.
And so, to conservatives, the federal
imposition of school bussing and forced
racial integration amounted to a
constitutional crisis with respect to
the guaranteed constitutional power of
the states. Additionally, conservatives
scorned the high tax rates required to
fund all these liberal policies. For
example, in the 1970s, the wealthiest
Americans were taxed at a 70% rate, and
to correct this, conservatives
championed supply-side economics, which
is a system that would lower taxes to
bare minimum levels and deregulate
businesses. And the idea was that if
America's businesses and entrepreneurs
paid less in taxes, then they would
invest that money into their businesses
and thus create more jobs. And in that
way, wealth would trickle down from the
richest Americans to the rest of
society. Okay, now the next thing you
need to know about this conservative
movement is that their intensity got
turned up to 11 once they got the good
Lord Jesus involved. What I mean is the
1970s marked an inflection point for the
melding of conservative new right
politics with the growing evangelical
Christian movement. As a result, the
Christian right emerged as a powerful
political force that opposed abortion
and condemned the secularization of
American society and supported a return
to traditional gender roles just as God
intended. Now, several high-profile
evangelical leaders played a big role in
blessing this union and I'll introduce
you to two of them. First was James
Dobson, who hosted an enormously popular
Christian radio broadcast called Focus
on the Family. And here, Dobson taught
his listeners that the Bible required
women to submit to their husbands and
commanded parents to enact strong
physical discipline on their children in
order to save them from turning to
secularism. In other words, women could
drink a tall glass of shut the heck up
and children could get a butt cheek full
of the spanking spoon. Anyway, in these
and many other ways, Dobson galvanized
the Christian right to embrace
traditional gender roles and thus save
God's greatest gift to the cultural
fabric of Western culture, namely the
family. And then the second influential
leader here was Jerry Falwell, whose
skillful use of television evangelism
gained him a wide audience among the
Christian right. So, in 1979, Falwell
founded the Moral Majority, which was an
organization that endorsed and supported
political candidates who promised to
uphold and advance called family values.
And since Falwell's audience was
becoming massive, new right politicians
started falling all over themselves to
partner with the likes of Falwell and
Dobson in order to receive their
endorsement. And so, in this way,
millions of American evangelicals were
convinced over time that a vote for the
Republican Party was a vote for Jesus.
And that, my dear pupil, is a potent
combination. And finally, I need to
finish up by telling you about the most
salacious and juicy political failures
of the 1970s, which all had the the of
plunging public trust in their
government to new lows. And there were
three categories of failure that you're
going to need to know. First, political
scandals seriously damage public trust,
and none was more corrosive than Richard
Nixon's Watergate scandal. So, Nixon yet
again tickled the fancies of his beloved
silent majority in order to win a second
term in 1972. But, at that very same
moment, Nixon was embroiled in a scandal
that would unravel many of the gains
that he had secured for the new
conservative movement. So, right after
the election, news broke that five men
on Nixon's re-election committee had
broken into the Watergate Hotel in
Washington, D.C. in order to steal
documents that belonged to the
Democratic Party and bug their offices
with listening devices. Now, Nixon
denied knowing anything about the
burglary, and that may have been true.
But, what was beyond doubt is that once
Nixon did find out about it, he
authorized an elaborate cover-up for the
crime. And even worse, Nixon ordered
federal investigators to turn their
attention elsewhere so as not to
incriminate the president. And so, in
light of all this, Congress formed an
investigative committee and ultimately
found that despite Nixon's repeated
claims that he was innocent, he was in
fact a real guilty and deeply complicit
in making plans to steal the election.
And therefore, when it became clear to
Nixon that Congress intended to impeach
and remove him, Nixon resigned the
presidency in disgrace in 1974. And all
this had the effect of convincing the
American people that they could not
trust their government officials. Since
Nixon turned out to be not so much a
president, but more like a damp fart in
the shape of a president. And then, the
second development that eroded public
trust in their government was an
economic crisis in the '70s known as
stagflation. And I talked about this in
my last video, so I'll keep it short
here. Basically, the group of Middle
Eastern states that made up the
Organization of Petroleum Exporting
Countries cut off their oil exports to
the United States, and that resulted in
stagflation in which inflation and
unemployment was rising at the very same
time. And because this was an economic
situation that had never before been
experienced, no federal policy seemed to
help it, and that made the government
look weak and ineffective. And finally,
third, public trust in government eroded
because of foreign policy crises, the
most notable of which was the Iran
hostage crisis in 1979. So, way back in
1953, the CIA had participated in a coup
in Iran that resulted in the overthrow
of their democratically elected leader
and installed the US friendly Mohammad
Reza Pahlavi in his place. And not
surprisingly, certain factions within
Iran were deeply resentful of this
foreign meddling in their affairs. And
so, in 1979, the disaffected Iranians
sparked a revolution that resulted in
the overthrow of Pahlavi. And in his
place, Ayatollah Khomeini assumed power
and represented a fundamentalist Islamic
regime that sought to erase the American
influence in Iran. Now, pretty soon
thereafter, Pahlavi was diagnosed with
terminal cancer and President Jimmy
Carter, humanitarian that he was,
invited him to the United States in
order to receive treatment. But Khomeini
warned Carter that if he allowed Pahlavi
into the United States, he would
interpret that as a hostile act from the
United States. Well, long story short,
Carter went ahead and did it anyway, and
in response, Khomeini ordered Iranian
troops to invade the US Embassy in
Tehran, and the result was that 52
Americans in the Embassy were held
hostage by the Iranians. And that's no
good, so Carter authorized a covert
operation to rescue the hostages, which
failed miserably. And as a result, Iran
held the American hostages for over a
year, a move that made Carter look weak
and ineffective, thus contributing all
the more to Americans' growing
perception that their government was not
worthy of their trust. And that,
combined with the burgeoning
conservatism that I mentioned earlier,
is going to pave the way for the
election of the brightest star of the
conservative universe, Ronald Reagan.
And that is where we're going to pick up
in unit nine. Well, okay, you can click
here to watch my other unit eight
videos, or you can click here to grab my
Apush Heimler review guide, which is
everything you need to study as fast as
possible. I'm glad you came around, and
I'll catch on the flip flop. Heimler
out.